{
  "reference_number": "13006",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The science is really pretty clear. Even staying within 2 degrees of warming globally will not guarantee irreversible changes in our\n Earth system in a number of different areas, so setting an ambitious target now is absolutely necessary."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The sooner we start dealing with our methane problem, and steering our economy away from emissions-heavy agricultural practice,\n\n the better. We don't have the luxury to wait."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "international carbon units only offsets the problem. The reality is that all countries are going to have to be pulling all the levers that\n they possibly can. Only a consolidated global effort is going to save this Earth from catastrophic climate change, therefore we need as\n\n many simultaneous efforts as possible. I'd also like to strongly suggest that a large proportion of the billion trees project is made up\n with long-lived native species, rather than a short-sighted effort to plant only radiata pine. Carefully managed native forests with\n selective and environmentally sensitive logging practices (as opposed to cut and clear) can provide a new high-value industry for New\n\n Zealand in the long-term."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under extreme circumstances and if new science comes to light suggesting that we have wiggle room. And of course, we\n should always be open to make it a more stringent target to reach if the science suggests that is what is necessary."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Bold targets, set in stone, will help drive innovation towards meeting them which can help our economy transition out of what is easy\nand comfortable. It will be a difficult transition for many New Zealanders, but this is the price we pay for decades of relative inaction.\n\nWe really don't have a choice anymore."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For the most part yes. What I feel is missing from the considerations is consideration of interconnected tipping points at a global level\n\n- one might lump this in with scientific information, but I think it is worth particularly spelling out that no one climate change indicator\ncan be considered in a vacuum. Consideration of Earth system processes as a whole, working in tandem with each other, is of\n\nparamount importance."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If you don't have a plan, there is less impetus to act."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most important thing to consider is that we, as a global society, are already many years too late to be arguing about the details.\n\nDrastic action is needed on a global scale, right now. The economy will suffer, people will suffer socially, and it the next few decades\nwill be a really difficult transition period. It's an unfortunate reality that we need to face up to, and is of course a very hard sell, politically\n\nspeaking. But anything less than a full commitment towards zero emissions, as soon as we can, is a crime against future generations\nand countless natural species."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Governments of the day will always be bound by party politics, and the fickle nature of voter opinion. An independent climate change\ncommission should be making these decisions itself."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "These seem like a good set of expert opinions to have at the table. Much like how the Land and Water Forum started out, with all\nvoices at the table. Unlike the Land and Water Forum though, all recommendations made by the Climate Change Commissioners will\n\nneed to followed, and this should be enshrined in policy/law. The Government should absolutely not be allowed to cherry pick which\nrecommendations they do or don't follow. If a suite of recommendations are made, it should be all or nothing (Hint: It should be all)"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "yes, this is a realistic and pragmatic approach"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely, the more we know about the problems and issues we are collectively facing, the better equipped we will all be to tackle\n\nthose challenges."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Overall, my view on what we need to do to address climate change, centres around planetary boundaries theories. There are tipping\n\npoints in all our natural Earth systems, and we need to stay within them. Essentially, all I want to say is summarised in this 4 minute\nspoken word poem performance, of a poem that I wrote summarising the Director of the Stockholm Resilience Centre, Johan\nRockstr√∂m's book, \"Big World Small Planet\". - https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yBjB-\n\nw5HD_M&t=0s&list=PLxTt2Nm5dTv3awnK1ren4BtHNctW_v7zY&index=11 MFE are most welcome to use this video to promote\naction on climate change. Changing the story - the narrative in our society - is just as important as changing the policy. Bring the\n\npeople with you, otherwise we have little hope. For the sake of all future generations, we must act, today."
    }
  ]
}
